<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rant on Aldrin Jenson</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/rant/</link>
    <description>Aldrin Jenson (Rant)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 19:27:40 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/rant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the ancients weren&#39;t morons</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/ancients-werent-morons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 19:27:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/ancients-werent-morons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: This is a personal opinion at this point in time and is subject to change with time and the constructive criticism I receive. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays most zoomers I&amp;rsquo;ve known both in college groups and in various online forums have this notion that the ancients especially in India were kinda primitive to the current generation and culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to gently disagree. It&amp;rsquo;s time to acknowledge that while we&amp;rsquo;re standing on top of giants, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily make us any taller than any one of the previous generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is the genZ with all &amp;ldquo;rational&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;logical&amp;rdquo; point of view says &amp;lsquo;Oh dude, the ancients/our ancestors used to practice stupid cultural traditions like Sati where the women had to jump into the pyre and kill herself if her husband dies as well. Now, isn&amp;rsquo;t that a horrible thing to do?? Surely the ancestors must have been plain stupid to allow those kind of practices to prevail!!. It&amp;rsquo;s so irrational, so they must be dumb.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How I&amp;rsquo;d like to interject here: &lt;strong&gt;No custom or tradition can sustain/continue for a sufficiently long period of time without a very reasonable cause&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, there must have been a good explanation on why traditions were continued for decades or even centuries.
eg: consider Sati. Let&amp;rsquo;s think about why this was happening&amp;hellip; did it happen because one day a king or a Brahman decided that from tomorrow onwards all women must kill herself if her husband died? Nope. That sounds ridiculous.
The ancient India consisted of many kingdoms where wars were pretty common. The women were considered as nurtures or nourishers who brings life to this world and cares for them. The men were considered as protectors of the land.
As a result, it were the men were sent to wars - They had to pledge the loyalty to the kingdom and had to take vows to protect the citizens from foreign invaders even if it meant sacrificing their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, think about it, what happens if the country loses the war? You all have seen the movies, what happens when the enemies defeat the home country? They loot out and take the gold and&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;and what , they kill all the man and&amp;hellip;? to take revenge of their fallen brothers and to please their lustful natures, they rape the women and torture the children, sometime often at the same place in front of each other.
See, this is the cause of Sati.. in ancient India, what happened to women after a kingdom lost a war was often worse than death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point I am trying to make is that, in order for any custom or practice or tradition to continue for a reasonable good amount of time, there would have been a very good cause for it. Without properly understanding what that cause was, if you try to call the people who practiced it as stupid, just because you think their practices were irrational, then it is you who is a dork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: Search about the actual cause for the origination of Sati and the reason it was continued for so long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s consider another example: In traditional Hindu homes, in the evening, there would be an oil lamp lit in front of the door. This practice has come down a lot and only very few Hindu homes still practice this and even recite ramaNama in the evening sitting near the lamp. According to the common genZ culture where one is free to choose any belief and religious practice of one&amp;rsquo;s liking, this may seems pointless and olden. Even from the last few decades, where being an atheist was somehow considered cool, this may seem&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
