<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on Aldrin Jenson</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Aldrin Jenson (Thoughts)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 00:45:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>People I think highly of</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/personal/great-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 00:45:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/personal/great-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A list of people whose selflessness and kindness has left a deep impact in my mind. These people never had to, bu still they took the effort to go the extra mile to do something for me. And it&amp;rsquo;s never about me. They would have done it eitherways to any single person.
In this world where everything is being more and more transactionary, I am grateful to have met these few people who have shown so much kindness and selflessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NP
Nithyalakshmi P (aka NP)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arul Murugavel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Titty Jacob Sir&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lekshmi Subha Ma&amp;rsquo;am&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sreekumar Sir&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gokulnath M. Prabhu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There are no bad People in this world</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/no-bad-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 06:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/no-bad-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to be someone who considers people as black and white - good and bad.
There are good people who are kind, helpful and overall nice. Then there are bad people who are the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, right now, I don&amp;rsquo;t think this approach is right.
No no. I am not saying there is a gray area for everyone. Instead I am just implying that the concept of classifying people based on their &amp;ldquo;niceness&amp;rdquo; or good-ness may be outright invalid. not wrong, but inapplicable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-beginning&#34;&gt;The beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started with an epiphany after reading the first chapter of the famous Carneige book for finding friends where it said: Never Condemn, criticize or &amp;lt;&amp;gt; a person. You never know what they are going through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading through all the principals shown in that chapter, I was able to relate a lot of my own life.
Surprisingly, I was able to relate to a lot of movie example as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1: take Cobra Kai series which is a sequel of the famous Karate Kid movies.
Quick recap: In Karate Kid, Daniel Larousso is a kid who is bullied for talking to a girl. He learns Karate from Miyagi and later beats the heck out of the bully and then getting the girl. We all cheered when at the end Daniel san did a crane kick and knocked down the bully. Cobra Kai continues this story and talks about how the life of bully John. From his perspective, Daniel is the foreigner who comes and takes his girlfriend away from him, and disgracing him in front of his master!
Most of would never have felt this way. We almost always side with the protagnoist of the story as the &amp;ldquo;hero&amp;rdquo;. Those who are agains the protagonist will be &amp;ldquo;villains&amp;rdquo; and hence the bad guys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another example of bully actually not really being a bad guy. In the movie &amp;lt; of 2 brothers with brad as a boy innocent and dirk as dirk the jerk bully&amp;gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many movies have been made where we see things from the &amp;ldquo;bad guy&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; perspective and we would be able to relate to their actions as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another example..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion--afterthoughts&#34;&gt;Conclusion / Afterthoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few questions may arise after reding through these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this mean all people are saints?
Nope. Just as all people cannot be labelled as bad, so can&amp;rsquo;t they be labelled as good. Because, classifying &amp;ldquo;good&amp;quot;ness is not possible. same as &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;quot;ness is not possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this mean that we should trust everyone?
Nope. I don&amp;rsquo;t think so. After multiple instances where a person has let you down, maybe it would be wise to not encourage that person to do so again. There would be multiple reasons for that person to do so. The point is not criticize and label a person as bad just because of this reason. Move on. Don&amp;rsquo;t argue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t argue.
No good has ever come up by arguing. Sure you should explain your point of view. But make sure that you tell it by not considering the other person as someone who have done something terrible and hence you consider them as someone beneath you. Don&amp;rsquo;t do that. It may surprise you to know that the other person may be having the exact feeling about you!.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything on the internet Is Fake</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/everyone-is-fake/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2022 22:35:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/everyone-is-fake/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you admitted that you were an asshole?
Oh wait, you don&amp;rsquo;t even think that you were such a person&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-people-are-fake-and-the-world-is-unkind&#34;&gt;The people are fake and the world is unkind&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is selfish. People want their on stuff to be prioritized.
Sure sometimes a few people may be kind to others by helping them in times of need, but that is only after considering if they are bored at that moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Else it&amp;rsquo;s just them saying excuses to keep away from someone who&amp;rsquo;d need their help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like this world and this kind of people..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why can&amp;rsquo;t everyone be more genuine and open.. Ahh, I get it. It&amp;rsquo;s because everyone want to maintain good connections with everyone else so they side with people during good times. However when&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the ancients weren&#39;t morons</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/ancients-werent-morons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 19:27:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/ancients-werent-morons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: This is a personal opinion at this point in time and is subject to change with time and the constructive criticism I receive. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays most zoomers I&amp;rsquo;ve known both in college groups and in various online forums have this notion that the ancients especially in India were kinda primitive to the current generation and culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to gently disagree. It&amp;rsquo;s time to acknowledge that while we&amp;rsquo;re standing on top of giants, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily make us any taller than any one of the previous generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is the genZ with all &amp;ldquo;rational&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;logical&amp;rdquo; point of view says &amp;lsquo;Oh dude, the ancients/our ancestors used to practice stupid cultural traditions like Sati where the women had to jump into the pyre and kill herself if her husband dies as well. Now, isn&amp;rsquo;t that a horrible thing to do?? Surely the ancestors must have been plain stupid to allow those kind of practices to prevail!!. It&amp;rsquo;s so irrational, so they must be dumb.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How I&amp;rsquo;d like to interject here: &lt;strong&gt;No custom or tradition can sustain/continue for a sufficiently long period of time without a very reasonable cause&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, there must have been a good explanation on why traditions were continued for decades or even centuries.
eg: consider Sati. Let&amp;rsquo;s think about why this was happening&amp;hellip; did it happen because one day a king or a Brahman decided that from tomorrow onwards all women must kill herself if her husband died? Nope. That sounds ridiculous.
The ancient India consisted of many kingdoms where wars were pretty common. The women were considered as nurtures or nourishers who brings life to this world and cares for them. The men were considered as protectors of the land.
As a result, it were the men were sent to wars - They had to pledge the loyalty to the kingdom and had to take vows to protect the citizens from foreign invaders even if it meant sacrificing their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, think about it, what happens if the country loses the war? You all have seen the movies, what happens when the enemies defeat the home country? They loot out and take the gold and&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;and what , they kill all the man and&amp;hellip;? to take revenge of their fallen brothers and to please their lustful natures, they rape the women and torture the children, sometime often at the same place in front of each other.
See, this is the cause of Sati.. in ancient India, what happened to women after a kingdom lost a war was often worse than death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point I am trying to make is that, in order for any custom or practice or tradition to continue for a reasonable good amount of time, there would have been a very good cause for it. Without properly understanding what that cause was, if you try to call the people who practiced it as stupid, just because you think their practices were irrational, then it is you who is a dork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: Search about the actual cause for the origination of Sati and the reason it was continued for so long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s consider another example: In traditional Hindu homes, in the evening, there would be an oil lamp lit in front of the door. This practice has come down a lot and only very few Hindu homes still practice this and even recite ramaNama in the evening sitting near the lamp. According to the common genZ culture where one is free to choose any belief and religious practice of one&amp;rsquo;s liking, this may seems pointless and olden. Even from the last few decades, where being an atheist was somehow considered cool, this may seem&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
